welcome to post doom regenerative
conversations exploring overshoot brief
grounding and gratitude I'm your host
Michael Dowd and in this conversation
recorded in November of 2019 I speak
with Daniel forsen Daniel is an amazing
young man and he has a podcast called
emerge making sense of what's next and
even though he's about the age of my son
I consider him an older brother on the
podcast path he is absolutely gifted and
so I encourage you to check that podcast
down he's also with the monastic Academy
which I'll read from their websites is a
say a center for training wise powerful
and loving leaders for an unstoppable
force for social and environmental
[Music]
enjoy this conversation
Daniel what a delight to have this
official conversation in this post doom
series I just greatly enjoyed that
getting to know each other call back a
couple months ago and one of the things
I'd love to do at the start here before
we get into the kind of questions that
I've been asking you know all the guests
in this in the series I'd love to have
you introduce yourself because some
people won't have read you they're not
familiar with your podcast and so help
us sort of you know don't be your normal
humble self like actually let us know
who you are what's your what's your
commit you know what's your what you're
particularly passionate about or
interested in these days yeah sure so my
I think my biography will be a little
bit less lengthly
lengthy than some of your guests and I'm
32 years old so I haven't too much yet
and I guess that the two strands of my
life that I can kind of point to that
are probably relevant for this
conversation are the work I've done in
social and systems change movements
these of the Occupy Wall Street and
cooperative housing you know and
creating various communities taking part
in various communities and then the kind
of more spiritual side where I've lived
for about now oh my gosh five years in
kind of intensive meditation communities
mostly in the Theravada Buddhist
tradition and I currently live at a
place called the monastic Academy in
Lowell Vermont was like very far north
in Vermont right at the Canadian border
where it's kind of like trying to figure
out what is a monastery for the modern
world and which I love that inquiry it's
really alive for me and then I also
probably the reason I'm on this podcast
with you now the reason that we were
introduced is because I myself have a
podcast called a merge where you know
essentially I started it off as an
inquiry that was something like you know
the world feels really broken I don't
really know what to do about that or how
to think about that let's talk to people
who seem to have some idea and I was
just sort of like follow my nose follow
the ear Oh swell
the curiosity that was alive you know
day-to-day week-to-week I would read a
book that really captured my my heart my
soul you know you know email I'd find
the email for the person be like hey you
want to be in a podcast and were some
reason that's persuasive to people in
today's world and they would go on a
podcast and I would get to talk to this
person I admired for an hour and a half
and you know those conversations
apparently have have resonated with
people it's that podcast his audience
has grown and in the process I have kind
of come to a sort of understanding or
vision of the state of play of the world
and the phase shift that is coming at us
whether we like it or not and I think
that's those conversations are probably
why we were connected you know speaking
with people like Jem Bendele and Vinay
Gupta
Daniel schmock canburger people who are
really sounding the alarm in in various
ways about what we're doing to the
biosphere what we're doing to really all
the systems that make our civilization
function I'm curious have you have you
had yet I only learned about this person
maybe Oh two weeks ago Barbara Cecil
sent me a an article that buy you a
comma la fille yeah he's beautiful
yeah yes I've ever had you know because
when you said you know sounding the
alarm
I love certainly that's what's needed
but also beyond that part of this post
doom series is it's not just sounding
the alarm because really as bio come
along he says you know the times are
urgent let us slow down you know indeed
and mechanic is not or even even a sense
of urgency isn't necessarily what's
needed now because urgency implies that
if we all if there's enough of us that
get together and do this one thing or
these few things then dot dot dot we can
avoid the cut yeah yeah it's almost more
like maybe I would say like turning on
the check the collective check engine
light you know like we we we ought to
all know we all recognize that the
fundaments of our civilizational
operating system are broken
and we need to do something about that
or at least we need to respond to that
and that might mean slowing down that
might be the appropriate response it
might mean sinking into presence and
going and living in a monastery but in
any case there needs to be an
opportunity for people to live in
relationship to this huge possibility
and probability perhaps what's
inevitable and then given what seems to
be inevitable or highly likely how can
we live our lives and have the best
quality lives the best quality
relationships the best quality
communities wherever that is for us and
the most soul nourishing ways to wake up
and go to sleep each day doing what we
can where we can and at what scale we
can because there's no shortage of
meaningful work it's just that if your
work if you still think it's about
saving industrialism from the
consequences of its own actions well
then right I'm gonna be frustrated
alright and right well and that's
something that so I went to I know that
you've connected with Joe Brewer I went
to his workshop in Costa Rica and that
was one of the questions right was that
it's sort of like what is passing what
in particular is passing away I guess
not I think the thing that I see with a
lot of my peers who I talk to about this
topic
it's like collapse becomes this almost
like binary zombie apocalypse where as I
collapse and then poof everything is
just gone it's like this this just
turning over of everything but actually
as you say there's opportunities in this
that I think we'd be wise to take a bit
take your damage in yeah what language
do you use or have you used what do you
find most helpful in terms of when you
speak and when you think for yourself
about these contracting and
deteriorating times yeah I tend now to
use the couple different terms one is
the meta-crisis omaree's nobody senate
crisis is the kind of collection of
crises that we're now facing yeah
the bundle and dad and the other is
phase-shift right and that leaves it
ambiguous whether we're gonna phase
shift into a higher order of complexity
or into a lower order of complexity but
that there's an inevitable phase shift
that's that we're coming upon and I
appreciate that because it doesn't then
sort of bias the interpretation of
what's what's happening it still allows
us to participate it you know into
existence yeah yeah yeah I like that I
mean I I personally don't think that
there's any possibility of a larger
order of complexity only because one of
the things I've been studying for the
last six years is energy and ecology and
there's always an upper limit to
complexity before you start reading the
energetic limits but nonetheless I like
that these sort of subtle ambiguity of
phase shift that's so that the your
reading of energy systems suggests that
we could not achieve a higher order
complexity civilization correct yeah
because we're already into we're already
more than a decade into the dirtier
harder to get much more expensive and
much more polluting aspects of dense
concentrated energy and there's no other
place in the solar system
you know people talking about mining
other you know asteroids and stuff like
that there's no we there's oh there's a
limit of every planet has a limited
amount of dense concentrated energy that
could be used and we've we're now into
the much more difficult harder to get
stuff and it turns out that there's an
energy per capita one of the whites law
in biology talks about that the
complexity of any system is integrally
tied to its energy use per capita yeah
so we're now in a decreasing energy per
capita and so there will be a decreasing
energy and it's it's as solid as the
second law of thermodynamics where do
you where can I read more about that uh
there was a guy Sid Smith Connie
literally just three four five days ago
just within the last week we watched a
Sydney I think it's be Sydney
did an hour-long presentation I will
send you the link and I'll put the link
in the in the description box of this as
well but that's fabulous also Nate
Hagen's Nate has a reality 101 course he
teaches students freshmen you know it's
an honors level course honor student
course at University of Michigan I mean
the University of Minnesota and he
covers energy just deeply its energy it
turns out that one of the things that
none of us have learned in our families
our churches our synagogues our you know
spiritual communities nor anywhere else
about energy and how ecosystems how
ecology works and that's that's the
piece the most significant authors in
that field without a doubt would be
William cotton and his book overshoot
the ecological basis of evolutionary
change and and so is your sense after
learning all of this and I mean I feel
like I almost want to
can I ask you questions is that what
you're absolutely is that there's no
shred in you that senses that we might
sort of thread the eye of the needle
here and graduate into a more elegant
civilizational design that's actually
more beautiful sustainable and you know
fully planetary no there's no shred in
me there's not one on a scale of zero to
a hundred on a zero on the possibility
and that comes from literally spending
30 to 40 hours sometimes 50 hours a week
over the course the last seven years
studying ecology and energy at the rise
and fall of civilizations
how was it for you growing up and then
how did you make whatever shifts you
made to the worldview that you now hold
yeah so I definitely was raised I think
even through osmosis with a kind of
sense of infinite growth infinite
progress and as soon as I graduated
college and started to live in a city I
lived in Washington DC I had I'd
recently started meditating and I was
sensitive enough that I think I could
just like feel in my body that something
was off about like cities and I couldn't
articulate it like intellectually I
didn't have a theory of why that was but
there was like something inhuman about
it or unnatural and and I left the city
and I went and lived in a meditation
center and eventually encountered the
work of somebody who's talking about
peak oil and so I got really into peak
oil for a while and then that didn't
work out like Peak Oil apparently didn't
happen and so for a while I had like
five years where I was like maybe I was
wrong like maybe we can keep going
maybe it's all chill I can get a job at
a software company and you know I did I
kind of like played the Millennial dream
of a decent job at a and making enough
money and living in a nice place I lived
in Boulder Colorado and I did that for a
while but then through the conversations
I had my podcast I became it became
clear to me that that was an illusion
that the way that I was attempting to
live was basically putting my head in
the sand and it was ignoring the reality
of what time it is on the planet and so
in order to be right with myself I had
to move back to the monastery and really
like
you know and whatever way I could live
in accordance with that understanding of
what we're doing to the planet and what
is real I suppose and yeah and so that's
kind of where I find myself now I'm
still maybe I haven't read to overshoot
so I don't I don't have the same kind of
certainty you have and I haven't done
the research you know I've talked to
people in podcasts and I have an
intuitive sense of like yeah the
impossibility of the way that we're
doing things the civilization that we
have now but I also do retain some kind
of like hope or that's not even hope is
the right word it's like trust or
willingness to be surprised by humans
and by nature like that there's a sense
of I don't know what's going to happen
more than there is a sense of doom
anymore I had a sense of doom for a
while I actually moved back to the
monastery being kind of carried by that
sense of doom but now when I check in
there's wonder and there's a sense of
like whoa what is going to happen like
stuff is getting crazy what's gonna
happen and there's interest and
amazement and curiosity but not know
certainty here yeah well I'm a thousand
percent with you in terms of the
cultivation and the grounding oneself in
trust whoa like aa sort of being
awestruck wonder interest curiosity I
love those and that's where I stay most
of the time
you mentioned peak oil one of the
greatest marketing successes in recent
decades is the very successful campaign
to discredit peak oil even though it
isn't and didn't get discredited I mean
it's not it's actually as real as ever
we're over ten you were 11 years or 12
years depending on I counted into peak
oil into peak conventional petroleum
sure I mean when I say that I was more
referring to the fact that the the the
the book that I read suggested that like
2012-2013 everything would just sort of
start to follow although I exactly know
there were many people who were speaking
from a peak oil perspective and yeah
more than that I never following Daniel
Pinchbeck I don't you're familiar with
his work yes return of Quetzalcoatl and
the whole 2012 mythology like I kind of
do there is there was a feeling in me
and I actually see this in a lot of my
peers like millennial peers of being
like fool me once you know with regards
to eschatology like okay maybe you know
and so there's this kind of like
suspicion of takes on it like especially
certainty right absolutely you know how
do you know like these things are so big
they're so complex like we'll figure out
a way through it and yeah for better for
worse that's kind of like when I talk to
people in my age or they're kind of like
well maybe yeah and that skepticism is
well-earned and his advisor
I mean I I one of the again I come back
to my favorite authors people like John
Michael Greer whoever had 15 or 14 of
his books and he is relentless on if I
keep wrote a whole book called
apocalypse not everything you know about
Nostradamus 2012 and the rapture is
wrong and he takes a look at the history
of apocalyptic thinking from when it was
first introduced 3200 years ago in
Persia and a takes a look at all these
different cultures and believing the end
of times and so yeah I mean the only to
my mind the only meme or the only set of
projections that's been more inaccurate
then anticipated into the world doom is
anticipated and projections and claims
of techno utopia that would probably be
the only thing that would be more in
error or more examples of well that
didn't happen you know I'm still waiting
for my jet but but I'd anybody watching
or listening to this I recommend William
I mean I recommend Richard Heinberg book
after burn society beyond fossil fuels
because Richard really is the elder or
certainly one of the great elder in this
field understanding energy and and he
also counts captain's overshoot is one
of the most important books he's ever
that young quest destinies but his
little book which I also recorded the
audio it's available free up on up on
Soundcloud
but after burn society beyond fossil
fuels really he even talks about he says
let's take a look at how well I did back
in 2004 with my first book on Peak Oil
the party's over and he takes a look at
the major claims there and sort of
reassesses them and so it's so what's
here I mean you're far more into this
world than I am you know I'm more
responding to it I think intuitively and
with my own just sort of like how I just
made a major life decision right to move
back to the monastery but like what are
you I mean if you're happy that you said
you've had 40 conversations in this area
so far like what are you seeing as
realistically plausible like near-term
futures like or I guess the question
that I used to ask to people on my
podcast I'd be curious to know what you
think it's like if you were talking to
you know some person around my age or
younger like how would you suggest that
they think about their future given what
you know yeah well given the fact that
my children are your age I've got a 36
year old daughter a 34 year old son and
a 29 year old daughter who just informed
me a month ago that she's pregnant
and and I also have an 8 year old
granddaughter so this is a great
question but this particular
caste is mostly me asking you questions
so I feel happy to be interviewed in
your podcast well I will say this that I
I'm kind of very close to Jim bundle
collapse of complex dissipative
structures is it absolutely guaranteed
it's a hundred percent inevitable it's
it's difficult because certainty is
relationally toxic and so I hesitate to
say that with that kind of certainty
because that sort of stops the
conversation it's sort of arrogant it's
it's just numerous and so and yet it's
not you know if somebody were to have a
conversation with me and say well no the
earth doesn't go around the Sun the Sun
goes around the earth you know you need
to have some epistemic humility around
that and well no actually there are
certain things that I use the word God
in reality interchangeably there are
certain things in reality to speak
mythically God has revealed to us
through evidence that are totally
compelling and it would be false
humility to say otherwise and one of
them is that complex dissipative
structures complex systems of any kind
there's a limit to complexity and the
limit is determined by energy and
ecological factors other ecological sort
of limits such as Lighting's law the
minimum that you know I don't want to
get into that but they answer your
question I see collapse not as something
that could happen might happen won't
happen collapses 30 years already
ongoing I mean both the most in your
life I mean basically since depending
upon where you started but it's
certainly the mid 70s to mid 80s and
really in some systems collapse since
the 1950s of the ecosystem so if you
look at the water the fisheries the
other species the insects if you look at
carbon in the atmosphere yeah I mean all
of these earth centered life yeah
measures yeah yeah that's very clear to
me too
I think that that we are already in to
collapse and it's a it's a stair-step
and there's partial recovery so that's
the way that virtually all civilizations
city-based civilizations and a city is
almost by definition a human
ecosystem that has overshot the carrying
capacity of its region so it needs to
draw on resources from outside to
sustain and so that collapse is already
ongoing and there will be you know some
larger downturns and then some shorter
ones and there'll be partial recoveries
that's why John Michael Greer's theory
of catabolic collapse is one of the most
elegant he talks about anabolic collapse
which is IDs overextend what they can
afford to maintain and they start
feeding on themselves I mean that's what
the Rust Belt is in the United States
the Rust Belt is it since 1970 the
United States has been post peak oil and
we are now catabolic we are eating
ourselves to death and that's just what
civilizations that's what city based
unsustainable civilizations do so for me
that is knowing that my children and
grandchildren are gonna have as long as
they live that's gonna be their reality
the reality is dominated by less and
less not more and more yes
it's likely to be challenging really
challenging but also what a lot of
people by focusing on that don't see is
that in previous collapsing
civilizations you do often see 2025 % of
the worst of humanity show up but you
also see 75 to 80% of the best of
humanity show up people are sacrificial
they're they're engaged in each other's
lives because we're all in it together
and you and your neighbors or your you
know the people in your community are in
it together most people respond in very
generous compassionate ways and local
source of meaning and so for example you
know I'm sure you know this because it's
your generation an entire generation of
sort of 15 to 35 year old young men not
just in the United States but throughout
the world the industrial world are
profoundly addicted to internet gaming
or internet porn or both well that's not
gonna happen when their communities need
them they're gonna be engaged because
their communities need them not gonna be
wasting time in front of a screen so so
I tend to focus on that that young
people children one of the things we
know about previous collapsing
civilizations is that that's when
saints sages heroes and Shiro's hmm ORN
it's like the womb for them who often
are then mythologized in you know a
hundred two hundred years later because
they were so exemplary in their
leadership and in their self-sacrifice
and in their love and compassion in that
process so I I think that collapse is
already ongoing that it's likely to be
really really challenging and anybody
who thinks that our species couldn't
possibly go extinct in the next 50 to
100 years isn't paying attention we may
last I actually think that there's a
decent chance that there will be pockets
of humanity throughout the world that
lasts but you know for another million
or two million years before some
asteroid or supervolcano or something
takes us out because no mammal our size
lasts forever
I mean most mammals our size last at
most 3 or 4 million years yeah so anyway
so that's sort of the approach and and I
invite people to really especially young
people to really get their hearts as
well as their heads around certain
things that are inevitable and don't
invest so that's why I have a whole
series of things that I do video and
otherwise what I talk about thus saith
reality let's say if you know what is
reality telling us is inevitable is
futile because you want to accept what's
inevitable hmm you want to not invest in
what's futile
let's genuinely futile and then you want
to be able to discern what's Pro future
and soul nourishing and then invest
everything you got in what's Pro future
and soul nourishing because that's going
to give you the most meaningful joyous a
peaceful life in the midst of
contraction and collapse glass is a
difficult word because we think of it
like this and it's almost never like
that it's you know it took Rome 320
years there laughs it was a standard
step that's what John my guru calls the
long descent anyway right so that's sort
of yes it's it's it's wonderful to
actually hear you reflect on this
because I think you've done a lot more
[Music]
kind of study of this topic and
but the the struck the broad-strokes
that you're laying out I feel like I'm
living into with my life right like the
way that I've changed the course of my
life to accord with what I was learning
in these conversations which for me more
than any kind of fact or you know
specifics about ecology was emotional
yes story reality that I was just like
faced with yes and that I had to then
reconsider the stories by which I was
living my life and yet for me as you say
there's a kind of heroic possibility
that I see in the story of collapse that
like calls me forth into a more
beautiful more meaningful life and
that's sort of how I have found a way to
meet collapse and my own existence right
and it's actually revivified a lot of my
day to day in a way that is beautiful
and I don't and it's funny like I don't
I was actually I just shifted the
inquiry of my podcast because I'm kind
of tired of talking about collapse
because it's not like I kind of I get it
like you and like I also love like you
know like this new piece around like
energy and ecology and overshoot like I
want I want to learn that but in general
like I'm more wanting to know like how
can I be more present with the people in
my life yes like what does it really
mean to be here and be human with each
other and it's like that seems really
amazing and hard and worth doing and I
know that in whatever world comes my way
I'm gonna be grateful if I had spent my
time doing that and that's seen that's
like you and then I can and then there's
it for me I noticed a sense of just like
like releasing of all of that I hope
that complexity right that it's so easy
for me to get invested into it just
floats away and then like here in the
middle of rural Vermont with 15 other
humans trying to be happy without like
living together and that's that's
that's it yeah well I wanted you to
share more about that in your monastic
experience and what you know how that's
happening for you up there I I will say
that I consider it graced with a capital
G sort of just the universe reality life
you know they sing Connie and I have had
this really weird lifestyle for 18 years
we've traveled North America we live in
other people's homes usually somebody's
second home or vacation home were there
for a month or two or three at a time
and then we speak in churches and
colleges and universities around that
and meditation centers and others you
know within a two-hour radius of
wherever we happen to be living so I'm
speaking to you for example right now in
Vicki Robins house in Langley Washington
on Whidbey Island because amazing yeah
we're taking care of Vicki's cat and but
but but but by having wealthy people who
have surplus housing mmm that have
offered us to stay for weeks or
sometimes a few months at a time at no
cost that has allowed us to become
independent scholars I mean I spent 20
30 sometimes 40 or 50 but recently only
15 to 20 hours a week in study of
complexity and ecology and energy and
collapse and whatever and and I wouldn't
I wouldn't be able to do that if it
weren't for the generosity of others who
are supporting what Connie and I are
doing in this whole epoch of evolution
sort of what we speak about because
Connie is a science writer and and her
passion is assisting trees and migrating
trees and migrating north faster than
any other animal can possibly move its
seeds and so turns out that hundreds of
species of plants and trees will go
extinct absolutely unless humans assist
them in migrating work or migrating
south of you in the southern hemisphere
but migrating poleward so it's holy work
building topsoil and planting trees
especially trees where you get the seeds
a little bit further south and you plant
them at further north this is holy holy
work yeah and
so what we speak about is where science
inspiration and sustainability intersect
but it's really only been the last seven
years that we've been in to collapse and
the sort of thing and by the grace of
life we've been given the opportunity to
really massively study this stuff and
interact with a lot of other people and
then many of the people who I've
interacted with and read are part of
this post doom conversation series yeah
well it's fascinating it one thing that
comes to mind too is you know I'm doing
research for an a podcast episode on the
topic of like Gen Z politics that's like
the generation after Millennials mostly
you know people they're in college right
now and younger and at least according
to this one researcher their politics
began with the assumption of the
collapse of society yes right and it's
how do they respond to it there's like a
right-leaning response that's more kind
of about acceleration ISM and it's you
know and then there's the more leftist
response with so there's a kind of like
a narco primitivism but in any case
there's the the younger generation
without any kind of as far as I can tell
very sophisticated like understanding of
energy systems or ecology or complexity
just knows in their bones that this is
destined for dissolution I'm curious
describe a little bit about your
experience your spiritual like one of
the questions that I often ask is what
spiritual tools psychological resources
what have you found supportive or
helpful and in your situation this
monastic I mean monastery is a word that
brings up for people something that may
not be accurate in terms you know we're
experiencing what you all are doing
there so yeah help us think and feel
into what you mean by monastic yeah well
I like the quickest way to give you a
sense of what life is like here is just
to quickly go through this schedule
which I'm pretty good at I can do quite
quick so that's good you know we have to
be downstairs in the Zen dough at 4:40
a.m. we chant for about an hour then we
meditate in silence for an hour and a
half then we have an hour of exercise
then we have breakfast which lasts for
45 minutes exactly
then we have a work period during work
weeks we work from about like 9:00 to
1:00 p.m.
they have lunch we have some chores
we've about two and a half hours of
break that's what I'm talking to you
right now is on our break and then we
have an evening program which is usually
an hour and a half kind of workshop or
it could be more meditation and then
followed by another hour and a half of
silent meditation and then a 15-minute
chant and then we go to bed and do it
all over again what's cool about this
place is you know most monasteries that
I'm aware of are you know they're kind
of just the only practice and technology
they really leverage his meditation
meditation is a primary thing we do here
but we also do a practice called
circling which is like interpersonal
meditation relational meditation we do
some trauma work together and all of
this is held in the context of like the
residents the people who are training
here are running a non-profit so like I
have just as much complexity in my
day-to-day as most people who are like
working in a start-up nonprofit which is
quite different than most people's
vision of a modest area someplace that's
just like so they're totally you know
simple like you're just making bread all
day or I don't know what it is but you
know so there's a lot of complex we deal
with a lot of complexity here we may we
used to make software that taught
mindfulness in public schools for
instance so a little bit more like
modern than most monasteries end up
being we're also not actually Buddhist
were basically post traditional we use
somebody the pedagogy of somebody named
Shin Zen Jung who has created a whole
approach to meditation inspired by the
spirit of science
everything is very methodical and kind
of categorized and demystified and it's
all the definitions are very particular
you know things like that and yeah so
that that's you know what life is like
here just to give you a little sense
yeah that's fabulous I'm so glad that
you did that because one of the things
again that I've appreciated about
reading histories of the rise and fall
of civilization Arnold Toynbee
Oswald Spengler
couple T of T stood eco and most of this
was I was introduced to through John
Michael Greer and he talks about the
monastic form being perhaps the most
resilient and a stable form in
contracting civilizations in societies
and through dark ages that's right well
so and so the other piece to bring in is
that the full name for the this
monastery is called maple which stands
for the monastic Academy for the
preservation of life on Earth and the
whole idea of the the founder whose name
is sore you for all and he's just coming
out of a two-month solitary retreat
tomorrow actually so we're kind of like
preparing to welcome him back into
community life the whole idea of it was
that he acknowledged from a very young
age that basically we were destroying
the planet destroying the possibility
for life to continue as it is and he saw
exactly as you say that monasteries were
the most resilient form of human
organization he said he will always say
like you know civilizations rise and
fall while these monasteries just
continue on Amen it's amazing no it's
incredible and so perhaps we can create
the same kinds of conditions here yeah
well and it's not even a matter of
perhaps we can create I mean you guys
are creating and others are too but it
becomes again natural selection is that
when the conditions when the
environmental conditions are such that
monastic communities thrive where other
forms of organization don't monasteries
will be popping up like new yeah yeah
and we're already seeing this actually
there's a whole new wave of monasteries
I think III expect that we're just like
the tip of the iceberg I think that
there will be many many many many more
such kind of organizations in the coming
years and I'm hearing you know various
kinds of chatter about them emerging
it's really fascinating yes exactly I
mean assuming that climate tipping
points don't really wag out in the most
severe ways right
that's absolutely count honorable yeah
again we learn this partly through
history but also through understanding
evolution and what the conditions are
that then
allow for or facilitate the emergence
the title of your podcast emerged but
the emergence of forms of organization
that thrive best in various conditions
yes yeah yeah yeah that's right and and
I think you know for me I talked to
somebody on my podcast about collapse
and they said that one way to think
about it is that it's like falling down
a hill like a large hill right and it
might happen in fits and starts like you
might fall down a portion and it might
really bruise you and then you'll stand
up to you like alright I'm okay and then
you'll fall down some more and you just
keep going you keep going and one way he
suggested to meet that challenge is just
to walk in the bottom of the hill right
just walk to the bottom a hill and and
there's a way in which I think that
monastic training affords a little bit
of that Sensibility right so many people
in our culture are addicted to so much
that the idea of say like losing the
ability to use Instagram for a week is
anathema okay and so you can go and and
hear like we can just just you know D
grow our life essentially and you know I
will tell you you know from personal
experience you can be happier than you
would imagine possible doing nothing for
a week
nothing and so that even just that
should reorient anybody's relationship
to like things so any any those three
human nature the big picture or
impermanence and death that you want to
just share anything on yeah I mean for
me the impermanence and death one is
it's really fascinating to me because
you know in Buddhism which is to the
tradition that I mostly practiced and
that's like its supposed to be a daily
recollection you know you say something
like I remember that my body is subject
to aging and death and thus I practice
you know to work out my salvation or
however you want to phrase it and for me
as somebody who was like practicing when
they're like 25 years old I was always
thinking like yeah I guess but you know
I got a lot of time it's gonna be fine
maybe we'll invent some kind of cure for
death by the time I get real old like 50
years old or something
breakers well certainly yes some people
are still going for that fantasy to live
in perhaps but but but the the way that
collapse has acted as a forcing function
for me to contemplate my own demise has
been incredible and I think that's been
a large part of what has allowed me to
kind of re-enter my life in this second
simplicity that I find myself in where
it's just like Oh Who am I with who's
here can I be with you you know and and
so what I've what I've found is that
actually those those recollections of
death have become much more potentiated
knowing what I now know about what we're
talking about and I've also added in
recollection about the impermanence of
our civilization as a daily recollection
just to kind of remember at this point I
think it's kind of like you I I no
longer take it for granted it's very
much like I go and walk around right if
I'm in an airport everything just seems
like I'm like oh my goodness like look
at this house of cards that's so
incredible amazing amazing amazing and
yeah so that it's been interesting for
me I think as somebody who's on the
younger end of the spectrum to really
feel like perhaps death is actually
something coming much sooner than I
would have thought even five years ago
back when you were talking about
voluntarily walking to the bottom of the
hill reminded me of my favorite books by
john michael greer which is actually a
some of his blog post didn't make it
into because he posted the art on the
Archdruid report every Wednesday night
for like 11 years he posted on the
arcuate report and they were like 5060
thousand of us that waited to see his
posts every Wednesday night and I've
recorded like 400 of them I think but
one of his books is titled collapse now
and avoid the rush
exactly the best good report exactly
that that sense of being so not just at
peace with reality but joyously
celebrational of reality as it really is
including its challenges including its
death and its end this being at peace
with mortality with death with
impermanence is is utterly invaluable
it's one of the first steps that I
encourage but again at people your age
people hasn't younger 20-somethings
don't I mean I I had a I was given a
gift that when I was 21 years old or 20
maybe I was 20 years old I was on top of
a mountain outside of Frankfurt Germany
and you know had one of the you know
most amazing mystical experiences of my
life on the top of this mountain um
where I was given a vision of my death
even if I lived a hundred years and it
was totally life-changing I you know
most 20 21 year olds don't think about
mortality and I was I was given that
gift and it's made a huge difference so
I did take a training with Joanna Macy
where we did it some exercises in deep
time yes and there's something in that I
think that still resonates for me like
sometimes I'll be meditating and I'll
just get the perception of myself as
that part of the earth that breathes
like this and there's it's less about a
kind of temporal cosmology and more a
sense of like yes I am not so different
than any of this that I see and and
there's a great piece in that for me in
coming to terms with the cascading
problems of overshoot resource depletion
climate breakdown etc have you
encountered stages of grieving that went
beyond mere acceptance like what what's
opened up for you on the other side of
the post doom doorway there is this
simplicity of being human that I've at
least for the time being seem to find
myself in where it's like yeah you know
this is gonna end but here we are now
and we get to be alive and there's a
kind of gift a good gratefulness in that
that's extremely sweet I think it's more
sweet than it ever was before yeah and I
actually haven't had that thought before
but it does seem that way like that that
that seems true to me yeah much more
precious last question what's your take
the it really is the question that you
asked me before that I refuse to ask if
you know what's your take on what's
beyond our control like and where we
still can make a difference individually
or collectively in other words what's
your sense of what's no longer possible
but then what still is possible I
haven't read some of the things that
you've recommended today and so I might
need to recalibrate my vision of what's
possible based on what I have yet to
learn but I do think that people that I
see you talking to and I don't I don't
I'm not so familiar with your work to
know whether or not you account for the
role that exponential technology could
play as it encounter some of these
collapse dynamics but frankly I'm I'm
I'm unsure I'm unsure what the future is
going to bring maybe it's a lack of
understanding but it's also just a my
information ecology is perhaps a little
bit too wide like I see things from so
many different information sources I see
so much technology that's being created
that seems like it might solve
particular dynamics and people are doing
this and people are doing that and so I
don't know what's possible but what I
what I do know is worth dedicating our
time to is is rebuilding the social
networks that exist in locations like
where I grew up in upstate New York
and that's what I plan on doing when and
if I leave the monastery right it's just
sort of like weaving those social ties
together so that you know no matter what
happens we go through it together
yeah and so I think that no matter what
your vision of the future is we're gonna
be better off if we have strong
pro-social groups that are thinking and
feeling and responding to the world
together and that's really for me like
the only thing that I feel totally
confident investing in it's like the the
the the human skills in how to do that
so for me that means healing healing my
trauma you know waking up growing up
cleaning up and then the actual like
time spent in intimacy working together
that builds those kinds of groups so
that's really you know that's all it
feels like it's definitely worth it like
everything else to me seems like a
crapshoot but yeah yeah well I'm so with
you on that I'm glad you mentioned the
word technology because we didn't touch
on that before when we were talking
about energy and ecology and overshoot
another resource that I would recommend
just the summary you don't even have to
read the whole book the summary he's got
a four page summary that's absolutely
fabulous but it's called techno fix why
technology won't save us or the
environment and it's by Joyce and
Michael Houseman I don't know if I'm
pronouncing their last name right but
you know they got dozens of people that
including Richard Heinberg and many of
the other people that are on the
forefront of these issues turns out that
human centered technology technology
that benefits us hmm what that is
harmful or or or toxic or in some cases
just even neutral but if it doesn't take
into well into consideration the
well-being of other species so it's
anthropocentric human centered
technology always creates more problems
than it solves it just does it over time
the only forms of technology and I and I
encourage anybody who is not sure about
that
two examples that are counter-examples
haven't I put that challenge out for
quite a few months I've never had
anybody been able to do that even
starting a fire or Spears hmm so human
centered technologies always create more
problems than they solve and it turns
out that technologies need energy and
use when you start unpacking the energy
commute home well I I want to be clear I
didn't just mean like physical material
technology I also mean social technology
yes and things like that I used that
more broadly like technique like ways of
being together would be - that's great
news for me so I yeah I'm aware of what
you're saying but yeah I mean there's
the whole realm of biomimicry and
mimicking the wisdom of these
technologies there's lots of different
ways to design technology that's one of
the things that Daniels bodkin Berger
talks about is how do we design
technology in a way that accounts for
its consequences yes and those kinds of
pro-social technologies if what you mean
by technology includes those social
dynamics yes there's there are profound
ways of organizing ourselves to for
example elicit collective intelligence
rather a collective stupidity that's
right and the emergence of something
genuinely novel but genuinely life
centered Pro future yeah and that's what
I hear daniel trachtenberg are
explicitly calling for is AI minus a is
more complexity in terms of the social
organism than in terms of the energy
system any final things you want to say
before we give this one a close you know
that right now the snow is falling here
in Vermont and it's just so beautiful
and I like fog rolling through the hills
and I'm looking out into the trees and
it's
like this whole conversation I think I
just there's been a sort of silence in
me and and I there's a way in which I
don't care about these ideas like I used
to and there's a part of me that's
ashamed of that and there's a part of me
that feels like that's actually the
right move now it's just to like live in
a way where I I know but I don't care or
something okay you haven't really worked
it out but I'm noticing this kind of
strange position I find myself in at the
end of this conversation for more
information about this project go to
post doom com